Finding Aid for the Ralph Bellamy Papers PASC.0224
UCLA Library Special Collections
Ralph Bellamy papers
1926-1982
1980-1982
UCLA Library Special Collections
Bellamy, Ralph
PASC.0224
1.0 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Ralph Bellamy has acted on stage, film, and motion pictures. The collection consists primarily of materials related his role in the television mini series Winds of War, including scripts as well as production and press material.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift.
Organization and Arrangement
The files are arranged alphabetically by file titles which reflect the contents of the folders.
Biography
Born in Chicago, Illinois on June 17, 1904, Ralph Bellamy began acting in high school. Upon graduation, he embarked on a theatre apprenticeship, touring the country and playing over 400 different roles over the course of nine years. Bellamy later moved to Hollywood to pursue a career in motion pictures, starring in over 83 films including Spitfire, The Wedding Night, His Girl Friday and Boy Meets Girl from 1930-1942. In the early 1940's Bellamy became disenchanted with Hollywood and, though successful, left to pursue other acting interests. Though Bellamy would continue to act in the occassional film, such as Rosemary's Baby amd Coming to America, the majority of his career from 1942 until his death was in television and stage productions. Arguably his most famous role, Bellamy portrayed President Franklin D. Roosevelt in both the stage and screen productions of Sunrise at Campobello in 1958 and 1960 respectively. Bellamy also portrayed President Roosevelt in the 1982 television miniseries The Winds of War. Throughout his career, Bellamy garnered multiple awards for his performances including a Tony Award for Sunrise at Campobello, a best actor award from the Academy of Radio and Television Arts and Sciences for Man Against Crime in 1950, four Emmy Award nominations and an honorary Academy Award in 1987 for his contributions to the industry. In addition to his acting career, Bellamy also participated in the Screen Actors Guild, as a founder and board member, and Actor's Equity, as president. A dedicated performer, he continued to work until the year before his death, acting in the film Pretty Woman in 1990. Ralph Bellamy died in Los Angeles, CA of lung disease on November 29, 1991.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9944361783606533
Scope and Content
The collection consists primarily of material related to Ralph Bellamy's role in the television mini-series Winds of War. Including in the collection are scripts and ephemera from the Winds of War television production,as well as small amount of articles and ephemera related to Bellamy's career.
Actors -- Archives.; Television scripts.; Bellamy, Ralph, 1904-1991--Archives.
- Aftra Magazine, (1983) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  General note
  See pages 6-7.
- Biographical Information, (no date) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Scope and Contents note
  Copies of Bellamy collection finding aids from Wisconsin State Historical Society and Boston University along with additional sources of Bellamy material. Photograph of Bellamy holding Life Magazine, and list of credits (1922-1983).
- Clippings, (1978-1982) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Empire Magazine (Mar 1978), Chicago Tribune (30 Nov & 12 Dec 1981), Los Angeles Herald Examiner (26 July 1980), Los Angeles Daily News (12 Oct 1981), and Good Old Days Magazine (1982).
- Emmy Magazine article by Richard Maynard, (1982 Sept-Oct) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  See pages 41-48.
- Harry Truman Conference, (1983) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Hofstra University (April 14-16, 1983) along with a letter from William F. Levantrosser, Hofstra University, to Bellamy.
- Hollywood Stuntmen's Hall of Fame charter membership certificate, (no date) (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Life magazine featuring Bellamy on cover and article, (1958 Feb) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  See pages 91-94.
- Palm Springs Life article by Anne Etheridge, (1977 Oct) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  See pages 64-66.
- Theater Programs (2), (1926, 1959) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  The Goose Hangs High, Princess Theatre, Des Moines (Nov 1926). Sunrise at Campobello, Curran Theatre (Nov 10, 1959).
- White House luncheon invitation honoring 100th anniversary of the birth of Franklin Roosevelt, (no date) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  With letter from Edmund S. Muskie.
- Winds of War - Emmy nomination certificate for Outstanding supporting actor in a limited series or special nomination, (1982-1983) (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Winds of War (Part I): The Winds Rise, (1980 Mar-1981); Revised script, 168 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Winds of War (Part II): The Storm Breaks, (1980 Sep-April 1981); Revised script, 124 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Winds of War (Part III): Cataclysm, (1980 Sep-April 1981); Revised script, 115 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Winds of War (Part IV): Defiance, (1980 Sep-Nov 1980); Revised annotated script, 120 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Winds of War (Part V): Of Love and War, (1980 Sep-Nov 1980); Revised annotated script, 123 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Winds of War (Part VI): Changing of the Guard, (1980 Sep-April 1981); Revised annotated script, 126 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Winds of War (Part VII): Into the Maelstrom, (1980 Sep-Nov 1980); Revised annotated script, 172 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Winds of War (The) - invitation to screening at Lincoln Center and ephemera, (1983 Jan 27) (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Winds of War (The) - publicity, (1983) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Articles from Hollywood Reporter (April 1983), Time (Feb 1983), The Times-Daily (Jan 1983) and a review from the Philadelphia Inquirer (Feb 1983).
- Winds of War (The) - Roosevelt speech, (1940 June 10) (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Winds of War (The) - shooting schedules and staff, cast and crew lists, (1981 Sept-Dec) (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Winds of War (The) - snap shots of ship and Bellamy on ship (3 items), (no date) (Box 2, Folder 4)